I'm not at all worried about the end of
apps. I think the bar for design and
product will get higher and higher and
that's a great thing because you're
going to have a lot of this like
AIdriven product design and then you're
going to have real professional design
that rises above and there's a like a
really clear zeitgeist right now the
anti-slop zeist and people wanting to
use things whether it's in the physical
world or digital world that are high
quality and thoughtful and doubling down
on product and design.
>> Hello, I'm your host, David Bernard. My
guest today is Jeff Morris, former VP of
product at Tinder, now founder and
general partner at Chapter 1, the early
stage venture firm for product obsessed
founders. On the podcast, I talked with
Jeff about Tinder's $50 million paywall
win, why now is such a great time to
build apps, and how hard payw walls can
mislead you about product market fit.
Hey Jeeoff, thanks so much for joining
me on the podcast today.
>> Yeah, excited to be here.
>> So, you tweeted a few weeks ago, a
banger of a tweet, and immediately
afterward, I was like, I got to get you
Jeff on the podcast. I I think I had
DM'd you in the past about coming on the
podcast. Um, but we finally made it
happen. And so, I wanted to kick it off
with that tweet. So, the tweet I think
for to some people might be a little
controversial in 2025.
>> Love that.
>> So, I won't steal your thunder. Why
don't you just tell me about what you
shared in the tweet and why you think
those things and I'm sure I'll have a
million follow-up questions.
>> Yeah. So, I guess like a bit of
background before I go into the tweet is
I ran revenue at Tinder for 4 and a half
years through kind of our hyperrowth
years. And so, I spent a lot of time
thinking about monetization,
subscriptions, and revenue obviously.
And what worked at Tinder and when we
really started to kind of like turn on
monetization didn't happen till year
years four or five um into the product.
And so we had built just a a great
product that had extreme product market
fit. We had scaled the product to you
know like 30 to 40 million monthly
activives but we didn't have a huge
focus on monetization. I think the
playbook at least until like call it AI
native applications started to come to
market was to really spend time on
getting the product right starting with
the just like the core engagement loops
and then making sure that you had great
retention to kind of earn the right to
to build a subscription business or
monetize through inapp purchases or or
advertising. I think there's a lot of
external reasons why founders now are
are pushing monetization earlier. market
is so competitive and so the I think the
metrics that you need to raise capital
have changed and so the revenue slopes
are much more extreme but you're seeing
teams now focus on monetization really
on day one as a even within the first
session there's a part of it which is
also like hey these businesses are are
really expensive to operate and the
model costs for compute and inference
require early stage founders to push
monetization earlier in the funnel. And
what's really interesting too from that
perspective is you're seeing a lot more
testing with within kind of like what
models do you offer consumers within
subscription tiers. So do you give users
access to your best performing model
that might cost more than other models
or can you convert them with lesser
quality models that are cheaper? And so
there's this whole new subscription
playbook that I think frankly
subscriptions were um like it was always
hard to monetize a user base. But the
packaging and cadence of a subscription
road map I think was a bit easier when I
was operating in 2015 to 2020. We now
invest in a lot of applications and I
meet with the teams and hear their list
of of kind of like challenges or
concerns with monetization and the
questions they're asking are just really
different from what prior kind of
platforms we're thinking about. So
whether it's mobile or um or kind of
like B2B SAS or anything bottoms up on
kind of like productivity type of app.
So yeah, and then the last comment I
would say is just there's a lot of like
uh celebrating around revenue today like
which I would say maybe is a bit
premature because you see either on
Twitter or within pitch dejacks like the
front page is hey we got from like 0 to
10 million in 3 months or 6 months or
whatever it is and then you kind of like
look at the data room or start to unpack
what the cohorts look like and they're
really new cohorts. So, it's impressive
that founders are reaching those revenue
numbers so quickly, but the jury is
often out as to whether the vibe revenue
or real revenue. And so, I think there's
going to be a lot of things that happen
in the next year, whether it's a
companies coming back to fund raise
where the the numbers don't look quite
as as advertised.
>> Yeah. And I think that's what really
resonated with me about your tweet and
kind of this whole idea is that
focusing first on engagement and
retention and then monetization
is it's not always the way to go. But
what's beautiful about that is that you
don't get a false sense of product
market fit. And that's what I do think a
lot of apps today that are launching
with a hard pay wall think they have
product market fit because people are
paying but then they bleed customers out
the back end and like retention is even
worse and so so I mean there's not I
don't think there's a right answer for
the entire industry but I do think more
apps probably should be experimenting
with premium models early like some
should be experimenting early if the
costs just don't allow you to do that,
if you haven't fundraised or whatever,
maybe you just can't and maybe you need
that revenue upfront. But for some
businesses, they're maybe shooting
themselves in the foot over monetizing
because there's people who might get
into your product and actually enjoy it
and be that long-term retaining cohort.
But by monetizing up front, you kind of
push them out and never get that chance
to win them back. And then you get
people who are willing to pay money to
try it out but then don't retain. And so
you're getting a lot of mixed signals.
Whereas if you can build from premium
from the start with that focus on
engagement and retention from the
beginning, you're getting potentially
getting better signals of like actual
product market fit. Whereas with annual
subscriptions, you might not really
understand just how bad your retention
is until 12 months later. And there's
hints of it. you can look at autorenew
status and stuff like that. Um, but any
kind of additional advice or thoughts on
like who should be trying that free
model first versus maybe the apps that
do work better with that flipped on its
head monetization, engagement,
retention, which seems like most apps
are kind of doing that today.
>> It's very much depends on the category.
If I was building an app today and um
I'd probably build more premium
experiences that have that don't
sacrifice product quality if you were to
monetize. So example being like there's
a website builder I know well they're
more of an earlier stage company and um
it's a really popular product within its
segment but the challenge they have with
premium was just users so if you build a
website whether it's on like a lovable
or a bold you obviously have like a fair
amount of debugging that you have to do
within any product that you create and
they actually couldn't afford to let
their premium users debug the initial
builds. And so if you look at like
Twitter for that product, people were
really frustrated because they would
have some idea, they'd prompt the app
and then it would be buggy and then
they'd be kind of like pushed into some
subscription to to kind of make that
happen. Like there's not a payoff of a
successful outcome before you're asking
people to open up their credit cards.
So, I think for something like that, I
would probably just say, "Hey, we want
everybody who pays for the product to
have like really have full access to the
best working version of our product."
And so, you're kind of getting people
who are trying to monetize before they
have that that like magic moment with
their customers, which, you know, like
at Tinder, you wait for somebody to get
a match and to have a conversation and
to really believe in the product before
you ask them to to become a paying
subscriber. And so I would almost focus
less on total like subscription number
in terms of users then but really try
and provide a great experience for those
people who are willing to pay early on.
I think you I think you can still build
like very successful call like whalriven
products. These aren't even whales.
They're just people who really have a
high intent, like a they have a problem
that they really want you to solve
rather than being like, you know, like a
GA product that is suboptimal that
people complain about on on Twitter.
>> Yeah. And I I you know, a really good
example of this, people listening to
this podcast probably don't not many
listeners also listen to Ben Thompson U,
but he's been talking a lot about how he
thinks um Chat GBT should monetize more
via ads and probably should have from
the beginning. And one of the points
he's made that I think is really
insightful is that most people who use
chat GPT have never gotten to experience
thinking pro or deep research because
those aren't available on the free tier.
And so they don't even know what chat
GPT is even really capable of because
they've never paid. And so it's kind of
to your point, it there is a little bit
of a um
not chicken before the egg, but it's
it's like you you want your you want
your users to actually get the best
possible experience to really understand
what the product is, but that's
attention because how do you how do you
give that away for free or you know I
mean free trials kind of work but then
again it's like not everybody wants to
start a free trial and that kind of
thing, but how do you how do you get
those users that best experience of the
product to understand what it's even
capable of so that they know what
they're paying for um before they pay
and and maybe CHIPT is at a scale where
it it's okay and they the revenue grown
tremendously, but it's a it's a tough
balance. I mean, what are your thoughts
on like how to balance that that like
putting good stuff behind the payw wall
but still providing the best possible
experience?
>> Yeah, I think it's a a really hard
question. I think this is a version of
the world that favors the founder or the
company that can just raise a ton of
capital and has um you like we saw this
within ride sharing right and kind of
think of as being a similar thing where
if you were Uber or Lyft you could
subsidize the early cost then become
more efficient over time and you know
within kind of like AI applications I
think the same could be true where
you're seeing startups really struggle
to offer a great product because of the
the cost requirements as as opposed to,
you know, a founder who can raise a lot
more. So, I can think of like a recent
example where a founder raised, I think
they raised like a $50 million series A
from a big firm and they have an
identical product to a startup I know
and they're able to just offer better
experience because they can either
subsidize a premium product or be more
generous with a subscription tier within
kind of like classic subscription
products. If you're not building an AI,
there's a whole different playbook. So I
think it's it's probably good to look at
the world like between u call like AI
native comput inensive companies versus
the rest of if you're building continder
or a headsp space or something similar
you it's kind of like the classic
playbook and and you don't have to worry
as much about these new questions that I
think founders are are trying to figure
out. Yeah, it it is tough when things
are expensive. And I'm I'm curious your
thoughts then on raising money as an app
in 2025 because, you know, as you said,
if you can raise money and offer an even
better free experience, build up the
usage, build up the engagement, build up
the the product retention, and then
monetize down the road. For some
companies, that is the optimal path. But
raising money in 2025, [laughter]
unless you're an hot AI startup, is is
challenging. So, what are your thoughts
on on what sorts of apps can and should
raise in 2025 to run that playbook
versus, you know, a lot of the folks
listening are the more bootstrap and do
have to make these really tough
trade-off decisions. I mean, my my
weather app that I work on on the side,
I have like really high data costs.
Like, to get good weather data, it's
very expensive, especially like
animating the maps and stuff like that.
So I you know I personally face this
challenge and don't I have a hard pay
wall right now in my app specifically
for the cost reason similar to a lot of
these AI native apps but yeah how do you
avoid that in 2025 like how who can
raise money and who should raise money
to start with that kind of more premium
experience
>> yeah I think the um venture market is
treating nonInative apps as almost like
a non-investible category which I think
is pretty busy because we all know that
mobile use usage and adoption is growing
year-over-year. I think the knock on
mobile apps is just people there's a a
perception that people aren't
downloading new apps with the same
frequency as they did maybe in the I
don't know the 2005 to 2020 period. I
think now is a great time to build a
like a hyper premium mobile experience
for every niche imaginable. the cost to
build an application and from an
engineering perspective has gone down a
lot and will continue to go down. And so
probably my my favorite example which
most of your listeners maybe maybe know
of is like flighty I think has done an
amazing job and um their founder has
been building that for probably almost
10 years at this point. But if you
travel a lot and you are a business
traveler, like Flighty is by far the
best travel app, right? That does have a
hard pay wall and willing to pay, you
know, 40 bucks a year expensive to your
business or whatever it is because it's
such a a high utility product. If you're
building something that's more, you
know, like social or less clear on what
problem it's solving, then you might
have a harder time asking the user to do
that. If you can't raise venture
dollars, then you should be confident
you're building a product that people
will pay for and you should ask people
to pay for it and see what the responses
and I'm a big fan of monetizing early.
>> Yeah.
>> In that sense.
>> Yeah. And you know, Flight is an
interesting example. It may have been
that you um used it at a time when it
was a more of a hard payw wall, but he
was actually recently on the launch
podcast, which is kind of a sister
podcast to this. And they have been
experimenting and he was actually on Ben
Thompson's podcast talking about this.
And he has he has experimented his way.
And maybe this is one of those kind of
examples too of like over time you do
kind of find that right fit. But he has
a really interesting model where now the
first flight is completely free
with all the pro features and then if if
I remember correctly some premium
features then get locked after the first
flight. And so it's just we like he had
to really experiment into this like
hybrid thing. And so maybe that goes to
our point is like there's not like a set
rule. You need to like you need to
experiment and be willing to experiment
and not just follow the patterns but
figure out what's right for your app
>> is that he experimented in his way into
this like weird kind of fremium where he
does
>> yeah that's almost like a like almost
like a trial to me. Um,
>> yeah, premium is like in my mind I the
definitions could be entirely different.
It's like you can use the app in
perpetuity,
>> but there's just different value that
the developer gives you for that
experience. It's actually very possible
that I did get that first flight free,
but because the kind of like free
version was so limited that it just
pushed me right into the the
subscription. Yeah, that that may be a
good example for highcost apps though.
Maybe maybe that's the playbook to
follow is to figure out a way to give a
a taste of that better experience even
maybe without a free trial but actually
like some kind of usage limited time
limited. Maybe that's something Chat GPT
has or should experiment with is is
giving you know one deep research a
month so people can experience that like
I mean deep research freaking
incredible. I mean, the stuff I throw in
there and the responses I get back, I
mean, I use it almost on a daily basis.
Things that I would otherwise spend an
hour or two researching, I throw into
deep research and get detailed notes and
links. And I I think a lot of people
just don't even realize how good it is.
And it hallucinates way less because of
how much it thinks. Maybe this is like a
new playbook people should start
experimenting with is finding ways to
give, you know, one or two hints at that
in the premium experience to kind of
offset the cost of it uh while still
kind of giving that better experience.
>> I think the truth is like most of the
really fast growing AI products are
putting out so many fires that
monetization isn't like it's not as
sophisticated as you think it is um
within those orgs yet. And so like we
have a portfolio company that's
I won't say the name but they hit 50
million in in AR within called a year
with a proumer product and I called the
CEO and I was like hey this is really
interesting like what are we doing on um
pay wall optimizations and pricing and I
started to like put my revenue hat on
and he was like what like just like what
are you talking about like we're and I
was like holy crap like you hit you know
50 million without any experience I'm
sure if you gave myself or anyone who
loves revenue, like just the keys to the
application for a couple sprints, like
we could probably like double your
revenue or do something uh that would
really like shock the team. And so it
kind of like reminded me that the
sophistication we got to at Tinder took
us a long time. like we when we really
like built out the revenue team it was
16 about a year into my my time at
Tinder and you know it's just like
myself and call like five or six
engineers right you had like three iOS
engineers and three um uh Android
engineers then leaving the company was
you know I think I had like 40 plus
engineers who were working on all parts
of the revenue road map um I think
that's kind of where a lot of these AI
companies are in their product journey
So, it's almost as we as we say that
like the a lot of them are trying to
monetize really early and then they kind
of do like this set it and forget it
thing where they're not like really
refining that part of their product. So,
I think it can lead to again even more
false positives or metrics that might
not prove to be durable over time.
>> Without revealing too much about that
startup, can you share like what your
first two experiments would be? I mean,
did did you go through the product
yourself and say, "Hey, here are the top
two I would run." Yeah, I think it was
mainly around kind of like packaging and
so they had a single subscription tier
and I found like our my biggest unlock
at Tinder was when I really started to
think of the subscription tiers in terms
of packages and all the way from like
the like the intra subscriber who's
probably younger and has less income and
maybe isn't in the US to like the most
uh the largest whale you can imagine,
right? someone who can spend like
$50,000 a year on a subscription
product, which we had at Tinder. But
that you're you're building for such
different customers, right? But that
just takes time to figure out because
you're you're you're not only building
kind of like new bundles, you're also
building new features. And so you're
trying to basically build very different
experiences for users with different
goals and expectations. Um, and you
could do that forever. like that's why
revenue teams are do what they do every
day. And then and the other the other
one that um they hadn't done was just
localization. So I think at at Tinder at
least like we had a really really
complicated pricing grid that was based
on a ton of different factors. The most
obvious being geography, right? Um so
knowing like our fastest growing markets
were Ladam and India but those markets
had a very different willingness to pay
to a North America or UK or something
similar. So I wanted to I did want to
dig into pricing and packaging. So let's
just move on to that topic in your work
at Tinder because we had Robbie Meta on
the podcast. So, what's funny is like he
got to build that really cool chart with
like the, you know, uh, higher price
tier, the mid-pric tier, the low price
tier, and then the consumable stacked on
top and like how it perfectly fits the
demand curve. But you were in the
trenches like building that from the
ground up. You know, he came along, he
did help with with that, but it's like
he came along and a lot of that had been
built. So, I did want to dig into a
little bit of like how that came about
like what were the experiments? What
were the conversations that led to the
three tier system and the consumables on
top of that? What was that process like
to get there? And I guess maybe just,
you know, frame it in a way that
listeners today can be thinking through
like how do I get to that kind of
multi-product? How do I better package
my offerings
um to fit those demand that demand curve
and the need of the users? I came in and
was basically given a spreadsheet which
had some really early versions of what
our pricing was like for a single
subscription tier. So it was Tinder Plus
at the time. Nobody was price testing
like that was just kind of what I think
we would probably run like a there was a
data scientist or scientists who would
run like really basic initial tests and
that's where they landed and it was kind
of like you know set and forget it.
where we really started to to focus on
pricing was as we started to saturate
the US market and really started to
focus on markets like India as I
mentioned and and LAM which were growing
but weren't necessarily the places where
we were monetizing really well and so
I'd say when you start when should you
start focusing on pricing I'd say like
really focus on your core markets and
you know for a US app developer
generally speaking unless you're
building a international specific app
like that's going to be the North
American America audience when we start
to expand the tiers like generally
speaking the product leads you to
premium features in terms of you start
to see what people are asking for and
what they want to what they want you to
build and then the question as a product
person is always is that something we
should monetize or or give away for
free. In the case of of Tinder, which
was specific to dating as a category,
there was a a certain element of, hey,
we're building a network and ecosystem
where if we give away everything for
free, the application simply won't
function. The kind of like gameplay of
the application starts to break down.
And so we had to think we had to think a
lot about like the second order impact
of any feature and how like what
percentage of the population do you
actually want to give that away to?
Because if you give everyone I'll give
like a real really obvious example like
we put a a payw wall on the number of
swipes you could do on a daily basis
because we found there were people who
were just swiping their way through
literally like their entire city in you
know like a very small amount of
sessions and so or you had things like
auto swipers and so um we put up that
payw wall to also to create a better
ecosystem but it also turned out to be a
great thing for monetization. So, I
think I think a lot of it is in terms of
like you should have like one or two
things that you charge for early on and
then really following the user and
following your power users in terms of
where they lead you for what they want
you to to build. Um, and we always
thought of these things as being like
superpowers that you could give the user
and obviously like you um not everybody
can have the full access to the
superpowers because then the
>> those features will become less valuable
to the the subscriber base. Yeah, that's
fascinating. Yeah, thinking of it as as
superpowers. What superpowers do I want
to give my users and kind of following
the product demand into building those
features? Did y'all ever experiment
during those years where you were like
hardcore, you know, optimizing the
revenue of pulling features in and out?
So, would you like put something in the
free tier and then oh wait, like we
really should have made that paid. How
did you run those sorts of experiments?
cuz those are hard and you know once
somebody's gotten something for free
then putting it behind the pay wall is
weird and then oh I paid for that why is
that now free how did you run those kind
of experiments
yeah I think we might have been a bit
different from like normal companies but
the revenue roadmap and our products
were very much built in like a different
part of the org we were on the product
team but like when we developed a
revenue feature it was kind of thought
of as being a part of the revenue new
product line that we we actually didn't
pull things in and out very often. There
were some cases where we thought we
could charge for something and then we
would look at the conversion data on
that payw wall and it just wasn't moving
the needle and so we would make it free.
But we never we never took something
from that was free and made it a paid
feature as far as I remember. I think in
most cases like people overthink the
like the user impact of a lot of these
decisions where you can like if you make
that decision to go free to pay like you
can always reverse that decision or
maybe you have like these moments of
where the users are like hey like I hate
that you you made this decision but if
you're solving a big enough problem like
they're going to stick with your product
and so you just need to do so in a way
that feels transparent and fair. like we
always like overthought um that things
we were doing would have like a bigger
like negative feedback than whether it's
price or anything else. And we just
always found that people were willing to
to stick with us as long as we gave them
a core product that still provided
value.
>> Yeah. And in our notes um that we're
working on ahead of the podcast, you
wrote something about that I thought was
really great. It was uh we spent too
much time building Excel features
instead of testing ideas. And I assume
that's what you meant like you you're
overthink things and uh run the models
and like price everything out and make
assumptions uh and overthink instead of
just getting out there and testing it.
Is that is that what you were talking
about? So we were a private company then
we be became a public company and Tinder
itself was the 90% of the revenue of
that public company. And so it was
actually a ton of pressure on us to
perform every single quarter. So you
basically had 12 weeks where you had to
deliver some revenue growth and if you
didn't do that literally like the stock
price would go down and everybody
everyone was mad, right? I think the
Excel version of this was we just had
more and more finance team members who
wanted to help us forecast the impact of
what we were doing. So then they could
go to the next earnings call and and
give a uh what would be a reliable
forecast. But that created I think like
a a bit of like a a Excel culture where
the product team was forced to kind of
like um spend a lot of time speculating
on things that were hard to predict. And
so um or we'd have things that would
happen in the quarter that were small
parts of our road maps going into the
quarter that would work in a really big
way that would make up for
any kind of like uh inconsistent
forecasting. So that was the biggest
thing was we kind of I think as your
company gets bigger, the word gets
bigger, you become a public company, the
stakes get higher and see you have to do
things with with more precision and um
in some ways that can slow you down for
sure.
>> Yeah, that's fascinating. I I we haven't
had too many publicly traded companies
on the podcast yet. something I'm I'm
working on. We're I'm actually
interviewing the the chief product
officer at Dualingo. It's going to be an
upcoming uh episode, so that'll be fun.
But yeah, imagine the pressure quarter
after quarter. It's just a whole
different ballgame than than most people
are used to. Uh I I did want to step
back and and you kind of dropped a
little something in there that I thought
was really interesting is that because
you were on the revenue team and the
features were specifically designed for
revenue. You you said you would like
test a payw wall and if those pay walls
wouldn't convert then you might make the
feature free. So you were doing testing
of like paid and then switching some of
those to free. What what would that look
like? It would be like the payw wall
would very specifically highlight this
new feature you built and then if the
conversion on those pay walls wasn't
high then you were assuming that that
particular feature wasn't valuable
enough to drive enough incremental
revenue that then maybe it should just
be pushed back into free is so that's
how you were testing these things. Yeah,
like pretty much every subscription
feature had a payw wall entry point that
we had a dashboard we'd wake up to every
day and we could see the number of of
obviously like the number of clicks it
got and then look at the conversion rate
and then map that to kind of like
incremental revenue for the subscription
product. And so you could see really
quickly like which products were getting
the most um attention and that that
could have been because like the payw
wall was positioned like we always
thought of as being like real estate and
so you have a a small canvas and a small
amount of real estate. is maybe the
problem is you don't you're not showing
the payw wall in a aggressive enough way
or it could simply be that people are in
the future and deciding that it's not
valuable enough for them them to pay
for. I think the what we kind of quickly
learn is it's almost like uh it's like
any like portfolio of companies or
products like there's a power law to
subscription features where one or two
features are probably going to drive the
majority of your new subscriptions and
everything else is is nice to have but
it's incremental. that could change.
Like I'm seeing a lot more creativity
with kind of like multi-product um
revenue lines. And I look at like Robin
Hood is a great example. It's not all
subscription revenue, but I think they
have 10 products that are independently
generating like north of $100 million
each. And so I look at that and but at
least when we were thinking about
Tinder, it was a lot a lot simpler. like
we had two to three power features that
people really paid for and then um we
would try and design you know more
features on top of those over time or
new experiments but it was pretty
consistent.
>> Yeah. One particular experiment that you
mentioned was uh a single experiment
that generated $50 million in revenue.
Uh tell me about that one. I mean, at
Tinder scale, maybe that wasn't and
maybe you can fill in the details there,
like how big the scale was, but tell me
about that one experiment that generated
$50 million.
>> Yeah, so we um probably in 2018, it was
actually a really fortunate surprise.
Tested a a toggle on the top of the
application where you could enter a new
subscription tier from the top navbar.
And obviously like you talk about real
estate that was a really premium piece
of real estate within the product and
people would tap on it and it was almost
like like we almost like discovered new
real estate because the design team was
really actually like didn't want us to
have that topnav which is always a
tension by the way right like you have
to have a beautiful product but you also
have to be creative in how you monetize
and so the
really was like we always had a a road
map as like small, medium, large XL
experiments like like everybody else.
And I would probably say that was like a
a small to medium experiment. It was
kind of a throwaway AB test. And you
wake up and you you look at the
dashboard I was talking about and you're
like, "Wow, crap. This is this thing is
really working." And those moments are
really fun. You can only like you get
some of that when you're working at at a
smaller company. I had the benefit and
fully aware of how lucky I was to be
working at scale with like 50 million
monthly activives and a product that
people were willing to pay for. So if
you tried putting like a top knot into a
meditation app, I'm not sure if it would
convert as as high as as what we're
doing. But the point is you should
constantly be thinking about where users
can access your premium features, where
the pay walls are placed. And often I I
find people are just like not thinking
creatively enough. Like you have a uh
maybe you have like something in the
some like nav um uh like buried in your
nav that that people just can't access.
And it always surprises me like I think
I think revenue team should be on the
whole like more a bit more aggressive in
terms of pricing and entry points
because again like if your product's
great, people are willing to kind of
like go along for the ride. you brought
up something in there that I wanted to
talk about next anyway and it is that
like balance the tension between
creating a quality product and like
caring about the users and the mission
and things like that but then also you
know monetizing and so it sounds like
that $50 million payw wall was a tension
in the company of the designers not
wanting the topnav pitch but h how do
you balance those things to keep the
product quality up while still, you
know, monetizing as effectively as you
can and then in your in your case doing
it while having a quarterly pressure
every 12 weeks to deliver.
>> I think there was a great culture within
our design team. We had a VP of design
who understood that we were trying to
design and build a beautiful product,
but we also were trying to build a a
large business in the process. And so
how how we thought about it a lot was
just like taking all the interactions
and payw walls and putting as much love
into those designs as we would any other
product feature. And so I remember we in
2017 we added like a animation to one of
our payw walls. It was like this gold
shimmer. It probably took a couple days
of engineering time and but people saw
them and and it it was a well-designed
payw wall, right? which I know is a um
not something that design teams want to
focus on, but we were like, if we're
gonna show a payw wall, we want that to
live up to the product, the core
experience, and and so we we tended to
like overdesign the the features that
other people would spend less time on. I
think that at least showed the users
that we cared about the experience. I
see a lot of payw walls that look like
they were designed in like by a PM, and
I just don't think that's how you
maintain product quality. The other
thing and I I'll say like I've seen it
more from a lot of products is is you do
start to get into the overoptimization
mode and um you start to grind users and
the product itself starts to feel almost
like spammy where you have too many pay
walls and I think that just comes with a
mature product that doesn't have enough
room to kind of grow and and you know
when you're a public company like you're
I think you can start to overmonetize
too. There's a trade-off. I was lucky in
in my in that role. I I think I departed
the company at the perfect time because
we were still growing a lot and it
wasn't kind of a more mature product. Uh
I don't think I would have been as good
in like the current years at doing that
job.
>> Yeah, it does. It gets harder and harder
as you mature, as the user base matures,
as competition matures, as the industry
matures around you. Uh it does get
harder. I did want to get to uh some of
your more recent contrarian takes and
one of them then is mobile isn't dead
and we've been hearing this since like I
don't know 2010 mobile is dead, mobile
is dead but you seem to think it's a
great place to build today in 2025. Why
do you think that? every kind of
platform has this like golden age
where there's so much opportunity and
white space within new categories that
you can build and consumers almost like
pull the product out of you right and we
saw that with mobile like I remember I
don't know in 2015 it's like you see a
cool new product an app and you're
always willing to give that to go
through the process of downloading and
signing up I think the I think people
have become like a bit jaded on the
consumer side as to try new products And
a lot of the big categories have become
obviously like very mature products that
are hard to disrupt. And so from a I
guess like an app developer perspective,
I think there's been on the ventureback
startup side less founders building like
pure play mobile products over the past
2 to 3 years where I think there's a ton
of opportunities. we have this new
platform shift which is AI and so you
can kind of reimagine new products. I
haven't seen personally and this is why
I'm so bullish a ton of like net new
truly AI native products that are mobile
first come to market. I think it's just
because we're like now getting out of
the infrastructure buildout to the
application layer and the first part of
the application layer was a lot of kind
of like vertical AI mostly web- based
products that that obviously like like
are doing well and now I think we're
finally entering the part of the market
where founders will start to there's
enough infrastructure there's enough
kind of like experimentation we'll start
to see really cool either consumer
products or mobile products for every
category. It could be things like, you
know, commerce, travel, social, like you
can kind of like canvas the app store,
the top categories, and ask yourself
like, okay, what if I redesign this
product? Like, what part of it could be
net new if I did did it in more of like
an AI native way? And so, I think that's
pretty cool. And I guess the last point
is that we haven't gone out of this
mobile design space where it's or sorry,
the AI design space where it's like
prompt to action. And so I think there's
a lot of opportunity within the new wave
of AI products, especially as we see
like better memory and context to
reinvent a lot of mobile products that
feel more personalized and feel more
predictive of what we want to do as
users.
>> And I I'll add to that too. I mean 5
billion people a day are on their mobile
phones around the world. Uh and they're
more open than ever to pay for software.
So it does feel like in addition to this
platform opportunity where AI is coming
in and allowing you to rethink things,
you're able to rethink things in a very
dynamic market. Sure, it's competitive.
Sure, it's hard, but when you succeed,
it can succeed really big. And then you
said very early in the podcast that
there is an opportunity and and I
totally agree with this for apps now to
be built in all these niches that maybe
didn't make sense during the kind of
quote unquote golden age of apps a
decade ago or whenever it was. So yeah,
I mean I I share your you're uh being
really bullish on the on the future and
there's just so much opportunity in the
space. What are your thoughts though on
how AI might subsume apps and those
opportunities? You know, flighty an
example like at what point does chatpt
have your calendar know when you're
flying? Are they going to build this
kind of stuff? Like what categories do
you think are kind of more at risk of
being subsumed by AI? And then, you
know, what areas do you think are are
safer to build in maybe? Yeah, I think
about it a lot like there's this belief
that maybe in a future where AGI exists
or you know advanced AI capabilities
exist that there's like not going to be
any interfaces. And I just think people
love to be entertained. They like to be
told what to do when they're using
products and they like using products
from people have strong opinions. And so
if you are a designer or builder who has
a a point of view on what the product
should look like and feel like, I fully
believe that people still want to be,
you know, shown a beautiful interface
and a really efficient workflow and that
we're not just going to have agents
doing everything for us. I also think
we're a very visual species. like we
when we're shopping or planning trips um
like there's some things that you don't
want to do in a interface that looks
like a ID or developer environment like
you again like back to the entertainment
idea like a part of this too is just
like we love to have a sense of control
and to to kind of go on that journey
whether you're buying a a new pair of
shoes or you're planning a summer trip.
I also just think, you know, people
might have more free time. And so,
again, what do you do when you have free
time? Like, you're probably going to be
using your phone a lot more and doing
things that are a lot more entertainment
focused. And so, I'm not at all worried
about the end of apps. I think the bar
for design and product will get higher
and higher. And that's a great thing
because you have you're going to have a
lot of this like AIdriven product design
and then you're going to have real
professional design that rises above and
there's a like a really clear zeitgeist
right now which is like the anti-slop
zeitgeist and people wanting things to
use things whether it's in the physical
world or digital world that um are high
quality and thoughtful and um well
designed. And so I think if anything,
doubling down on product and design and
and user experience will separate people
from kind of like the general purpose
super apps. And sure, I could track my
travel on chat GPT. I could probably
already do that, but Flight is just such
a compelling product that I'll stick
with that. Relatedly, one of your other
kind of contrarian takes is that there
are more apps and companies than there
are great ideas and that maybe more
people should be working together
instead of on separate apps. And may
maybe that's to this point. It's like
because the bar is raised instead of
being a solo founder just hacking it out
by yourself, finding other top people to
build with might help you achieve that
level of quality.
>> Yeah. I read this quote. It was like the
it's easier to raise money for a startup
than to get like a engineering job at a
top company these days. So there's
there's a lot of company creation and
there's a dispersion of talent that I
didn't have at least early in my career.
I think the, you know, like I remember
the days when like the Snapchat team was
so talent rich, like, you know, top to
bottom. It was almost like an all-star
team of of mobile consumer talent. And I
think now the incentive to start a
company and to do things on your own has
created a lot more companies than we
need to exist. And I'm hopeful that
people start to like talent consolidates
and we have really great smaller teams
working together. You see a lot of the a
lot of the big like the incumbents, the
Facebooks, even OpenAI have really great
talent across the board and they're just
able to pay a lot more money obviously
for that talent. I'm hopeful that we
have like these groups of, you know,
younger talented entrepreneurs who agree
like, hey, it's better if we're going at
a problem and maybe you have a
competitor going after the same problem,
like maybe you should team up and do it
together. Yeah, I think that's uh that's
great advice and it's it's tough because
there's so many I see so many
developers, you know, get to, you know,
2K and MR and 5K and MR. And I do wonder
if if like a group of of two or three of
them or, you know, somebody more product
oriented, somebody more designoriented,
somebody who's just like the hardcore
developer, if as a team they could kind
of break through that wall instead of
everybody thinking they need to just do
everything and be everything. Um, so
yeah, may maybe that's a good challenge
to folks listening to the podcast. Like
if your side project hasn't taken off,
maybe you need to collaborate more and
find some uh some talent to work with
instead of thinking you have to do it
all.
>> I It's definitely like I see these apps
and these stories of people getting to a
couple million million subscription
revenue as like a one or two person
team. And it's really cool that that's a
possibility. And so I think about that a
lot just personally like could I you
know if I wasn't a VC like could I pull
that off and what would that be like? I
think for me personally like I want to
do things at scale and so uh that
wouldn't kind of like satisfy me but I
can see how that would be for a lot of
people like a really great career
option. It just depends on the
personality and and kind of what you
want to do with your career.
>> Well I think now's a good time to kick
off the lightning round. I call it the
lightning round, but uh you don't have
we can have a discussion around these.
It's kind of a loose thing. Uh I've
started putting here at the end of the
podcast. Um the questions are more
focused on operators. So I'll ask this
in a different way for you, but the
question is generally what's your
biggest win of the year? So for you
maybe it's a portfolio company, a
biggest win a portfolio company had um
or just something you think people could
learn from that you saw in the past
year. Yeah, I think for us on the
investment side like the we were preede
investors in Suba Base which I think the
company's done an incredible job of
really leaning into what's happening in
AI and becoming like the database of
record for most major website builders.
um they've done so by being extremely
developer dri like the speed at which
they ship features they ship a new
feature every single day and so they I
think they set the bar for what
product velocity should look like and
just appears like like they won't slow
down personally I think the thing I've
loved doing is I've gone back to even as
a VC designing new products and so we
have a incubation which will be able to
to share next year, which was a has been
a ton of fun to work on because it's
been back in the Figma files and getting
um like really deep in product design,
which as an investor helps me stay
sharp. Like I don't know how I could do
this job and not still build things and
create things. And then we have another
product that we're releasing in the next
couple weeks which is more like a
venture scale product, but it's just
something that we're having a lot of fun
building. So, I think the lesson for me
is like I like all my energy that I get
is through building things and building
products and and investing, but I really
need to build things to be happy as an
investor, too.
>> That's fun. And it's interesting you
brought up superbase. I do think you
know this podcast is very focused on
building consumer subscription
businesses but some folks in our
audience might think about building some
B2B like what what things are you
frustrated with in the experience or
what holes are there what gaps are there
in the in the experience of consumer
developers and where could you fill and
superbase it's crazy how big they've
grown and how quickly they've grown by
filling one of those needs for the
market that already seems saturated So
it's it's pretty fascinating.
>> Yeah. I think a lot about just like day
one problems that every developer faces
and so you know like authentication
picking a database. We were early
investors in Mercury which is a bank for
startups like these day one decisions
and there's always going to be new pain
points to to solve there. And then as it
relates to the developer experience like
as you're building your subscription
products I'm sure there's a million pain
points that you have every single day.
And I found software when I was
operating to be like highly highly
inefficient from design through you know
product work to engineering deployment
post- deployment like there's so many
bottlenecks and luckily I think we're in
a moment in time where all that's being
kind of remixed in terms of the
functions and the workflows and so I
think there's a lot of opportunity to we
call it like the software factory but if
you think about the engineering cycle
and the production cycle of software to
really lean into what is changing today
and build new either B2B tooling or
infrastructure for those those new
problems.
>> Yeah. And at Revenue Cat, I mean, we're,
you know, we're trying to solve a lot of
those pain points and increasingly, you
know, building out new products and
stuff, but is there's still just so much
white space in in the industry. And to
our point earlier about consumer,
there's also space to think what's the
AI native version of solving this
painoint. What's the AI native version
of solving authentication or, you know,
other problems like Super did for
databases. The next question is what was
the biggest fail of the year or
portfolio company that you saw run a run
a maybe maybe one of the big fails was
not doing pricing experiment or
packaging experiment for that one
portfolio company but any other like big
fails that you think folks could learn
from
>> biggest failures always come come back
to product velocity and I think there's
a ton of pressure right now especially
within the venturebacked startup world
to ship things that are of a very high
quality on day one and so the you know
like I've heard this like idea that kind
of like uh iterating your way to product
market fit and like that whole exercise
is almost like uh we've kind of gone
back to like a world where you are
shipping extra-large day one products
and so I see I see some founders who are
like stuck in their own heads or
organizations as to to when they should
shift their product and almost waiting
too long and And the markets are moving
so quickly that if you wait too long
today, someone else is going to come in
and and and take that market. For me, I
think I think like we have to get back
to a lot more experimentation at the
application layer and and be willing to
kind of like make mistakes and not not
having to to kind of like have day one
perfection.
>> Last question. growth would be easier if
>> I think growth would always be easier if
you had like better day one data and
data systems in place. We've, you know,
I think a lot of the even up until like
I left Tinder, a lot of the business
intelligence questions and data
questions were still very hard to kind
of pull. Like we obviously like a lot of
us knew how to use SQL and could could
run queries, but I think a lot of the
actually like I've thought a lot about
this for this moment we're in in terms
of like can you use AI to basically like
recreate things that revenue teams can
do really well in a more efficient way.
So things like understanding your your
funnel better, um really knowing kind of
like what on the road you said like like
pricing, localization, like all these
things were actually really hard for us
to solve for I think are easier today.
And so growth would be I think a lot
easier if we really lean into this like
AI moment and tried to rethink the way
we operate revenue teams as an industry.
>> Such a great place to wrap up. Anything
else you wanted to share as we wrap up?
>> Yeah. uh if you're building a company
that's venture back like would love to
hear more. I'm JMJ on Twitter so you can
also follow me. I'm pretty active
online. Like I want to share as much as
I can about what we're doing. So follow
me there and lot of space you can find
me at Substacks. So I run a publication
called the new internet which I spend a
lot of time on as well.
>> Awesome. We'll link to both of those in
the show notes. Uh but thanks so much
for your time. This was a really fun
conversation.
>> Thanks David.
Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[music]